all right
[Music]
the burden of cardiovascular disease in
the African-American Community remains
high and is a primary cause of
disparities and life expectancy between
African Americans and whites why is
there such an excess burden because of
an excess burden of risk factors for
example high blood pressure diabetes
obesity and high cholesterol and what's
underlying those risk factors much can
be traced back to diet among the ethnic
groups the proportions of people meeting
healthy diet recommendations were
generally lowest among blacks in this
National survey most black Americans
were found to be eating a particularly
poor diet as defined by the American
Heart Association
African-Americans May face unique
challenges to adherence to dietary
recommendations and one such challenge
is an alignment with a cultural
tradition of soul food now some soul
food components are fantastic can't get
much healthier than collard greens and
sweet potatoes Tomatoes legumes and
dried peas and you know beans and black
eyed peas watermelon blackberries corn
okra it's all making me hungry but
conversely soul food can also behind
added fats sugars and salt with
prominent use of high fat Meats not to
mention the use of deep frying so like
you know fried chicken and chitlins
which are big intestines uh foods that
can be high in sodium and saturated fat
dietary factors linked to chronic
disease
where did the pig intestines custom come
from you have to trace the roots soul
food is what the enslaved Africans were
forced to come up with in the Deep South
to survive during slavery that's in
stark contrast to traditional West
African diets where they come from which
were predominantly plant-based centered
on a foundation of greens and fruits and
legumes and nuts and vegetables and
whole grains and even more vegetables
however these Traditions have been
westernized bastardized into a diet high
in fried foods sweetened Beverages and
bread and processed Meats
but the good news is more and more
African Americans are adopting
plant-based diets to combat their health
problems helped by a growing movement of
vegan soul food restaurants that serve
healthier plant-based meals soul food
scholar Adrian Miller even wrote that
after eating his way across the country
it was clear to him that Soul Foods
Creative Energy Burns brightest in
restaurants that are targeting upscale
vegetarian or vegan clientele
are they reaching the people who need it
most though well they do tend to be
located in higher African-American
higher poverty areas a significant
number of restaurants were classified in
food desert zones where there's a dearth
of supermarkets implying their potential
to provide healthier meals to Residents
in the surrounding neighborhoods
therefore having more vegan soul food
restaurants and growing movements
centered on black veganism May provide
opportunities to influence the nutrition
habits in the African-American Community
especially since some were even able to
offer cooking classes so establishing
Public Health Partnerships with vegan
soul food restaurants to get more
African-American adults to eat
plant-based Foods could be a promising
first step in reducing some of the black
white Health disparities we're not meat
shamers said owners of vegan soul food
restaurants promoting healthy eating in
the African-American Community were
plant pushers
trying to tie the best of Soul Foods
Origins to a 14th century plant-centric
West African diet in hopes of making
people feel that you know being vegan is
in fact a legitimate part of black
culture and black identity even
potentially tying it into the concept of
social justice in an attempt to reverse
the effects of targeted marketing
efforts by fast food companies to
children in communities of color this
movement has been helped by a plant
positive who's who of Black Culture not
just luminaries like Coretta Scott King
and Cory Booker but the likes of NBA
star Samuel L Jackson and Beyonce and
influentially the late activist Dick
Gregory known in popular culture as a
comedian but was also an outspoken vegan
Health Advocate influenced by alvinia
Fulton who imagined soul food that was
actually good for the soul instead of
celebrating the fact that slaveholders
denied enslaved people access to Quality
Foods she persuaded black communities to
view food as a agent of health and
healing advocating fresh Whole Foods is
the path to alleviating or reversing the
crippling burden of chronic disease
black vegetarians and vegans are showing
a plant-based diet isn't just for white
people and never was in fact you can go
back centuries to The Liberator back in
the 1800s the Abolitionist publication
where William Lloyd Garrison wrote his
famous essay I will be as harsh as truth
and is uncompromising as Justice
well in an 1853 issue it was written
that a man whose stomach is crammed with
animal Abominations can no more
appreciate lofty moral and intellectual
teachings than a swine can appreciate
pearl necklaces logic humor and
eloquence are wasted on such persons if
only the American people took more
thought what they should eat and drink
obeying the rules impressed upon them by
experience and Science by which they
meant a vegetarian diet America would be
half converted to anti-slavery peace
Temperance Land Reform women's rights
Etc in a single year
foreign